This is the bacteria finding: can a model warn us about unsafe beach water before the lab result arrives?
The lab measures Enterococcus, a fecal-indicator bacteria. It is a warning sign for possible poop pollution.
The old way is slow: culture tests are useful, but the result often arrives 18 to 24 hours later.
We used beach samples plus information that would be known in time: recent lab history, place, season, rain, and runoff.
The test was honest: train on older years, calibrate on 2020 to 2021, and report on the 2022-plus test set.
The model learns from features, which are clues like rainfall, runoff, beach history, season, and location.
The model gives a probability score, like a weather forecast. Adults still choose when that score becomes a warning.
The calibrated model beat the main operational baselines on average precision, with strong AUC and low calibration error.
AP, AUC, and ECE answer different questions: ranking rare events, separating unsafe from safe days, and checking probabilities.
A confusion matrix turns the chosen advisory rule into four outcomes: true positives, false positives, false negatives, and true negatives.
At the chosen threshold, the rule caught 86 percent of unsafe days and made about 3.35 false advisories per caught exceedance.
Changing the threshold changes the tradeoff. Lower thresholds catch more unsafe days, but also create more false alarms.
The hard part is avoiding both mistakes: too many false alarms, and too many missed unsafe days.
The chosen advisory rule is cautious: it catches most dirty days, but the false-alarm cost is stated plainly.
The science is not magic. The signal comes from past samples, beach-specific history, season, location, rain, and runoff.
A related finding says the target label matters: culture and ddPCR tests disagree at official cutoffs, even though they rank dirty days similarly.
What it means: the model can support warnings and sampling decisions, but people still choose the policy threshold.
What it does not mean: it is not a guarantee, not ocean magic, and not a final answer on which bacteria test best predicts health risk.
Bottom line: the model improves risk ranking, the confusion matrix explains the tradeoff, and the next science question is the label.