Here is the whole machine. We collect public data,
organize it in a lakehouse, transform it into clues,
choose target engines so the question is fair, run
model engines, and keep only evidence that passes
checks.
First, raw data lands safely. Beach lab samples,
weather, sensors, water quality, and research feeds
arrive before we change names, units, or dates.
The lakehouse has three shelves. Bronze keeps the
original files. Silver holds cleaned tables. Gold
stores model runs, predictions, metrics, and
leaderboards.
Transforms are the cleanup team. They fix units, match
stations, join sources by time and place, build
features, and block future answers from leaking into
training.
The folders act like rooms in a school lab. Source-
shaped datasets, silver tables, gold results, research
engines, reports, and the explainer website each have
a clear home.
Feature builders turn tables into useful clues: recent
history, rain and runoff, physics pi groups, tensor
factors, and oxygen covariates for stress screening.
Each target engine asks one exact question. Beach
bacteria, surprise-onset events, oxygen stress,
harmful algae signals, and state QA each use its own
grading rule.
Then the model engines compete on that target. Simple
logistic models, tree boosters, neural nets, tensor
factorization, and zero-shot readouts all get graded
against honest baselines.
A result is not trusted just because it looks good.
Holdout tests, baselines, confidence intervals, null
checks, calibration, and critic reviews decide what
survives.
Here is what survived. In tested held-out coastal
datasets, fixed physics clues ranked bacteria risk
better than normal-rate guessing. That is useful for
first-pass triage, not official advisories. On a
California surprise-onset slice, the model helped spot
recently clean beaches that later turned dirty. The
oxygen screen helped flag low-oxygen stress from other
water-quality clues. Tensor patterns helped check and
fill one tide-density sensor signal. The big
foundation-model story was dropped because it did not
beat simpler physics.